Guide to the American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina Records, 1960-2020; 1960-ongoing and undated RL.00012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Legal Program Series, 1968-2006 and undated, 260 boxes
  - General Counsel Office Subseries, 1968-1980s, 64 boxes
    - General Files, 1971-1974
      - Mental health: Department of Motor Vehicles (Box 93)
      - Mental health legislation (Box 93)
      - Military: Concerned Officers Movement (Box 93)
      - Military, general (Box 93)
      - Miscellaneous pleadings (Box 94)
      - Miscellaneous pleadings (Box 94)
      - The National Prison Project (Al Bronstein) (Box 94)
      - NCCLU Legal Foundation: litigation, general (Box 94)
      - NCCLU Legal Foundation: taxes (Box 94)
      - North Carolina Police Executives Association: proposed legislation (Box 94)
      - North Carolina State University: employment discrimination (Box 94)
      - Optician licensing (Box 94)
      - Outlawry (Box 94)
      - Penal reform legislation (Box 94)
      - Pending cases (Box 94)
      - Police misconduct: sub-file (Box 94)
      - Political: campaigning, etc. (Box 95A)
      - Politics and ACLU (Box 95A)
      - Pollitt, Professor Daniel, general correspondence (Box 95A)
      - Pollution (Box 95A)
      - Pre-sentence Diagnostic Study, NCCLU (Box 95A)
      - Prison abuses (Box 95A)
      - Prison System Study (Box 95A)
      - Prisoners: medical treatment (Box 95A)
      - Prisoners: access rights to newspaper, radio, television, etc. (Box 95A)
      - Prisoners' rights (Box 95A)
      - Prison regulations (Box 95A)
      - Prison libraries (Box 95A)
      - Proposed legislation (Box 95A)
      - Public use infringement (public parks, etc.) (Box 95A)
      - Publications, articles, NCCLU (Box 95A)
      - Racial discrimination (Box 95A)
      - Raleigh Chapter (Box 95A)
      - Real property (Box 95A)
      - Religious (Box 95A)
      - Requests for briefs (Box 95A)
      - Rights of children with special learning needs (Box 95A)
      - Robeson County Board of Education (Box 95A)
      - Robeson County Indians (Box 95A)
      - Salary garnishment for National Defense Student Loans (Box 95A)
      - School prayer cases (Box 95A)
      - Search and seizure (Box 95A)
      - Sedition (Box 95A)
      - Smith, Norman B., correspondence (Box 95A)
      - Sterilization (Box 95A)
      - Student rights, general (Box 95B)
      - Summer internship program (Box 95B)
      - Teacher problems (Box 95B)
      - Transcripts for prisoners (Box 95B)
      - Tuition residency (Box 95B)
      - University of North Carolina at Greensboro (Box 95B)
      - Volunteer attorneys, researchers, etc., NCCLU (Box 95B)
      - Voting requirements, general (Box 95B)
      - Woman's rights (Box 95B)
      - Women's rights in military (Box 95B)
    - Cases Closed Files, 1968-1974
      The largest group of files relates to nuclear power and lawsuit against Atomic Energy Commission. Original alphabetical arrangement. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files. As with other legal files, the names of defendants and others in some cases have been redacted from this collection guide but are present on folder titles in the boxes.
      - Death penalty (Box 96)
      - Conduct unbecoming an officer, 2 folders (Box 96)
      - Conscientious objection (Box 96)
      - Gender discrimination (Box 96)
      - Freedom of press (Box 96)
      - Housing discrimination, racial discrimination (Box 96)
      - Residency-election (Box 96)
      - Prisoner's rights, illegal detention, mental health (Box 96)
      - Voter discrimination (Box 96)
      - Freedom of assembly, folder 1 of 5 (Box 96)
      - Freedom of assembly, folders 2-5 of 5 (Box 97)
      - Freedom of speech, freedom of assembly (Box 97)
      - Conscientious objection (Box 97)
      - Freedom of press, freedom of speech, freedom of peaceable association (Box 97)
      - Illegal search (Box 97)
      - Freedom of press, freedom of speech (Box 97)
      - Cain, Charles J., et al. v. Robert Morgan, etc., et al. (Box 97)
      - Carolina Environmental Study Group v. The United States of America and the United States Atomic Energy Commission, folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 97)
      - Carolina Environmental Study Group v. The United States of America and the United States Atomic Energy Commission, folder 3 of 3 (Box 98)
      - CESG v. USA and USAEC (United States Court of Appeals for District of Columbia): pleadings (Box 98)
      - Carolina Environmental Study Group v. USA and USAEC:
        - Newsletters, clippings, etc. (Box 98)
        - Technical materials, radiological (Box 98)
          Includes files on radioactive emission and storage of radioactive waste.
        - Technical materials, general information on nuclear power, 2 folders (Box 98)
        - Energy budget and alternative sources of energy (Box 98)
        - Final environmental statement for McGuire Nuclear Station (Box 98)
      - Carolina Environmental Study Group v. USA and USAEC, cont.: (Box 99)
        - Reactor breach, China syndrome (Box 99)
        - Catawba Nuclear Power Station, York County, S.C. (Box 99)
        - Barnwell, S.C., nuclear fuel reprocessing facility (Box 99)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 99)
        - Pleadings, CESG v. AEC (District Court, Charlotte) (Box 99)
        - Notes (Box 99)
        - General correspondence (Box 99)
        - Ralph Nader et al. v. Dixy Lee Ray et al., Carolina Power and Light et al., intervener-defendants, and General Electric Co., intervener-defendant. (Box 99)
        - Proceedings before the AEC (Box 99)
        - Notes and memoranda (Box 99)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 99)
      - Freedom of expression, public school dress code (Box 100)
      - Housing discrimination, religious freedom (Box 100)
      - Habeas corpus (Box 100)
      - Police brutality (Box 100)
      - Death penalty, 2 folders (Box 100)
      - Freedom of expression, prisoners' rights (Box 100)
      - Involuntary plea, right to proper counsel, folders 1-3 of 5 (Box 100)
      - Involuntary plea, right to proper counsel, folders 4-5 of 5 (Box 101)
      - Attempt to ban all R and X films from drive-in theater (obscenity, freedom of speech), 3 folders (Box 101)
      - Alamance County, harrassment and discrimination against person with long hair at Holly Hills Mall (Box 101)
      - Seizure by prison guards of correspondence and print material relating to Prisoners' Union business, 2 folders (Box 101)
      - Resident versus non-resident taxpayers' rights (Box 101)
      - Depriving convicted felon of right to vote, 1 of 3 folders (Box 101)
      - Depriving convicted felon of right to vote, 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 102)
      - Denial of habeas corpus by State of NC, 3 folders (Box 102)
      - Suit against mental health treatment center at Butner Correctional Facility, still under construction (Box 102)
      - Denial of right to run for school board in Lincoln County, NC (Box 102)
      - Zoning, landfill near residential area:
        - General (Box 102)
        - Correspondence (Box 102)
        - Notes, articles, photographs, folder 1 of 3 (Box 102)
        - General, 5 folders (Box 103)
      - Prisoners' rights, review of personal file, folder 1 of 2 (Box 103)
      - Prisoners' rights, review of personal file, folder 2 of 2 (Box 104)
      - Separation of church and state, "So help me God" in oath (Box 104)
      - Freedom of speech, freedom of press, freedom of assembly (Box 104)
      - Greenville Police Department case, illegal search and seizure (Box 104)
      - Prisoners' rights, medical care, 2 folders (Box 104)
      - Conscientious objection, 4 folders (Box 104)
      - Discriminatory enforcement (Box 104)
      - Freedom of speech (Box 105)
      - Imprisonment for nonpayment of fines and court costs (Box 105)
      - Conscientious objection (Box 105)
      - Racial discrimination (Box 105)
      - Disturbing the peace (Box 105)
      - Inquisition case, freedom of speech, freedom of press (Box 105)
      - Right to speedy trial (Box 105)
      - Prisoners' rights, medical care (Box 105)
      - Prisoners' rights, medical care:
        - General, 2 folders (Box 105)
        - Court file, pleadings (Box 105)
        - Witnesses and documents (Box 105)
        - Miscellaneous and correspondence (Box 105)
      - Freedom of the press, folder 1 of 4 (Box 105)
      - Freedom of the press, folders 2-4 of 4 (Box 106)
      - Freedom of the press, 2 folders (Box 106)
      - Freedom of speech, freedom of the press (Box 106)
      - Prisoners' rights, medical care, folders 1-2 of 5 (Box 106)
      - Prisoners' rights, medical care, folders 3-5 of 5 (Box 107)
      - Unlawful boarding and inspection (Box 107)
      - Due process, barring from student teaching (Box 107)
      - Prisoners' rights, competence to stand trial, mental illness:
        - Correspondence (Box 107)
        - Pleadings (Box 107)
        - Correspondence (Box 107)
        - Pleadings (Box 107)
        - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 107)
        - Miscellaneous pleadings (Box 108)
        - Notes (Box 108)
      - Illegal seizure and sale by tax authorities (Box 108)
      - Due process (Box 108)
      - Illegal search and seizure, Miranda rights, 3 folders (Box 108)
      - Right to counsel (Box 108)
      - Police misconduct (Box 108)
      - Freedom of speech (Box 108)
      - Long hair in schools (Box 108)
      - Discriminatory enforcement (Box 108)
      - Right to counsel, racial discrimination (Box 108)
      - Freedom of speech, academic freedom (Box 108)
      - Power of convening authority (military), 3 folders (Box 109)
      - Residency requirement (Box 109)
      - Parade ordinance (Box 109)
      - Illegal dismissal for Ku Klux Klan membership (Box 109)
      - Long hair in schools (Box 109)
      - Illegal dismissal (Box 109)
      - Grand jury selection, due process, racial discrimination, prisoners' rights:
        - Affidavits (Box 109)
        - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 109)
        - Memoranda (Box 109)
        - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 110)
        - Miscellaneous, folders 1-4 of 5 (Box 110)
        - Miscellaneous, folder 5 of 5 (Box 111)
      - Illegal search, invasion of privacy (Box 111)
      - Due process, equal protection, double jeopardy (Box 111)
      - Denial of voting rights (Box 111)
      - Police misconduct, illegal arrest, probable cause:
        - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 111)
        - Notes, research, articles (Box 111)
        - Pleadings, 3 folders (Box 111)
        - Statements and exhibits (Box 112)
        - Witnesses (interviews and statements) (Box 112)
      - Illegal imprisonment (Box 112)
      - Conscientious objection, 2 folders (Box 112)
      - Case subject unknown (Box 112)
      - Racial discrimination against whites (Box 112)
      - Denial of admission to NC State University for political reasons (Box 112)
      - Prisoners' rights (Box 112)
      - Fair trial, due process (Box 112)
      - Illegal search (Box 112)
      - Unconstitutional expulsion, freedom of expression (Box 112)
      - Case subject unknown (Box 112)
      - Illegal imprisonment, commitment to mental hospital (Box 112)
      - Jury selection, jury discrimination (Box 112)
      - Parade ordinance (Box 112)
      - School districting, voting rights (Box 113)
      - Right to counsel (Box 113)
      - Parole revocation without hearing (Box 113)
      - Illegal search, 2 folders (Box 113)
      - Certification of candidate (Box 113)
      - Prisoners' rights (Box 113)
    - Requests for Assistance, 1968-1973
      Files arranged in original alphabetical ordering by individuals' last names.
      - Ad-Bu (Box 113)
      - Ca-McM (Box 114)
      - Ma-Wy (Box 115)
    - General Counsel Prisoners' Rights Project, 1974-1975
      Arranged in original alphabetical order.
      - Ac-Al (Box 115)
      - An-Bat (Box 116)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 116)
      - Prisoners' Project: Asheboro Unit (Box 116)
    - Cases Closed, 1975-1980 (Box 117)
      Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files. As with other legal files, the names of the defendants and others have been redacted from this collection guide but are present on folder titles in the boxes.
      - Solicitation of services, 1st and 4th amendment (Box 117)
      - Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation Service Committees: age limits for committee members (Box 117)
      - Race (Box 117)
      - Nudist camp (Box 117)
      - Housing, due process (Box 117)
      - Wrongful discharge of fireman due to hair length and dress (Box 117)
      - Removal of personnel files (Box 117)
      - Constitutionality of "outlaw" law, 2 folders (Box 117)
      - Power line across property (Box 117)
      - Convicted felon wrongfully terminated (Box 118)
      - Plea bargaining agreement not kept (Box 118)
      - Wrongful termination due to adoption proceedings (Box 118)
      - Constitutionality of interstate compact on juveniles (Box 118)
      - Student whipping, 3 folders (Box 118)
      - Missing persons against parents' wishes (Box 119)
      - Blanch prison case: prisoner treatment, 2 folders (Box 119)
      - Unconstitutional search (Box 119)
      - Hair length requirement for band (Box 119)
      - Wrongful termination, sexual discrimination (Box 119)
      - Wrongful termination, due process (Box 119)
      - Wrongful termination, due process: briefs and notes, 4 folders (Box 120)
      - Wrongful termination, due process: correspondence (Box 120)
      - Wrongful termination, due process: miscellaneous (Box 121)
      - Wrongful termination, due process: pleadings (Box 121)
      - Miranda rights, confessions (Box 121)
      - Prisoner legal services (Box 121)
      - Prisoner treatment (Box 121)
      - Prison conditions (Box 121)
      - Affirmative action (Box 121)
      - Right to treatment for children (Box 121)
      - Property settlement (Box 121)
      - Double jeopardy (Box 121)
      - False arrest (Box 121)
      - Wrongful termination (Box 121)
      - Redisctricting (Box 121)
      - Racial discrimination (Box 122)
      - Inability to pay filing fee for political office candidacy (Box 122)
      - Wrongful termination of voluntary fireman (Box 122)
      - Insufficient counsel (Box 122)
      - Carolina Environmental Study Group, legality of nuclear power:
        - General, 3 folders (Box 122)
        - General, 3 folders (Box 123)
        - Correspondence (Box 123)
        - Court orders (Box 123)
        - Court papers (Box 123)
        - Court papers, 3 folders (Box 124)
        - Drafts and duplicates (Box 124)
        - Legislative materials (Box 124)
        - Potential witnesses (Box 125)
        - Research materials, 2 folders (Box 125)
      - Challenges to jury composition (Box 125)
      - NCSU religious non-solicitation (Box 125)
      - The Charlotte Three, racial discrimination (Box 125)
      - Citizens Against Nuclear Power (Box 125)
      - Selling newspapers at a public school, 2 folders (Box 125)
      - Property rights (Box 126)
      - Mental patients operating vehicles (Box 126)
      - Prisoner treatment (Box 126)
      - Wrongful termination (Box 126)
      - Wrongful termination of a Socialist (Box 126)
      - Wrongful termination, 1st amendment (Box 126)
      - Wrongful termination (Box 126)
      - Child neglect (Box 126)
      - Racial discrimination (Box 126)
      - Unlawful imprisonment (Box 126)
      - Censorship (Box 126)
      - Declined request for assistance (Box 126)
      - Request for assistance (Box 126)
      - CWP grave markers (Box 126)
      - Prisoner abuse (Box 126)
      - Rights of white people (Box 126)
      - Rights of white people, 3 folders (Box 127)
      - Gender discrimination (Box 127)
      - Religious discrimination (Box 127)
      - Blacklisting and wrongful termination (Box 127)
      - Woman not allowed to vote due to former husband's residency (Box 127)
      - Wrongful termination (Box 127)
      - Prisoner treatment (Box 127)
      - Prisoner treatment (Box 128)
      - Academic credit during suspension (Box 128)
      - Wrongful termination (Box 128)
      - Wrongful termination, religious discrimination (Box 128)
      - Unlawful imprisonment (Box 128)
      - Unlawful imprisonment, habeas corpus, 3 folders (Box 128)
      - Racial discrimination, seat numbering law, 5 folders (Box 129)
      - Prisoner treatment, rape (Box 130)
      - Malpractice (Box 130)
      - Jail providing religious services to those who did not want them (Box 130)
      - Meeting room for Ku Klux Klan (Box 130)
      - Wrongful imprisonment, sexual orientation discrimination, 4 folders (Box 130)
      - Wrongful imprisonment, sexual orientation discrimination, 3 folders (Box 131)
      - Informant secrecy (Box 131)
      - Due process, student suspension (Box 131)
      - Court fees, defedent for plaintiff (Box 132)
      - Unlwaful home searches, 4th amendment (Box 132)
      - Denied request, habeas corpus (Box 132)
      - Police assault (Box 132)
      - Solicitation laws, religious discrimination (Box 132)
      - Forsyth County Public Library: Ku Klux Klan meeting room (Box 132)
      - 14th amendment, due process (Box 132)
      - Due process (Box 132)
      - Denial for assistance (Box 132)
      - Insufficient representation (Box 132)
      - Prisoner treatment (Box 132)
      - Sexual discrimination, residency requirements (Box 132)
      - 4th amendment, unlawful search (Box 132)
      - Residency requirements, 2 folders (Box 132)
      - Unlawful termination due to moustache and party affiliation (Box 133)
      - Denial of medical treatment to prisoner (Box 133)
      - Unlawful imprisonment (Box 133)
      - Prisoner abuse (Box 133)
      - Constitutionality of body execution (Box 133)
      - Guidelines for cooperating attorneys (Box 133)
      - Selective service system (Box 133)
      - Wrongful termination, refused to take polygraph (Box 133)
      - Legality of military activities in Asia, 2 folders (Box 133)
      - Plea bargaining (Box 134)
      - Divorce (Box 134)
      - Handicapped accessibility (Box 134)
      - Inadequacy of educational program (Box 134)
      - Habeas corpus (Box 134)
      - Due process, flight test for Marines (Box 134)
      - Habeas corpus (Box 134)
      - Unlawful termination of a government employee (Box 134)
      - Prisoner treatment (Box 134)
      - Mistrials (Box 134)
      - Termination due to political affiliation (Box 134)
      - House sale confusion (Box 134)
      - Unlawful sentencing of juvenile to training school (Box 134)
      - Prisoner treatment (Box 134)
      - Privacy Act, dishonorable discharge (Box 134)
      - Due process (Box 134)
      - Human Relations Interfaith Celebration (Box 134)
      - Residency for tuition (Box 134)
      - Divorce/separation (Box 135)
      - Prisoner treatment (Box 135)
      - Due process, cruel and unusual punishment (Box 135)
      - Wrongful termination due to dress (Box 135)
      - Level of prisoner security (Box 135)
      - Decline for assistance (Box 135)
      - Habeas corpus (Box 135)
      - Unlawful search and seizure, unlawful eviction (Box 135)
      - Mistrial, not allowed witnesses, 2 folders (Box 135)
      - Prisoner treatment, not given mail (Box 135)
      - Mistrial, evidence that had been improperly seized (Box 135)
      - Nude dancing (Box 135)
      - Segregation in prison, 2 folders (Box 136)
      - Prisoner treatment, cruel and unusual punishment (Box 136)
      - Prisoner treatment, due process (Box 136)
      - Requirement that notaries must believe in God (Box 136)
      - "Know Your Rights" (Box 136)
      - Citizen pulled over and threatened officers (Box 136)
      - Illegal search and seizure (Box 136)
      - Petition (Box 136)
      - Wrongful discharge due to refusal to0 wear "Free Joan Little" button (Box 136)
      - IRS religious discrimination (Box 136)
      - Political rally/riot, Communist Party, 4 folders (Box 137)
      - Denial for promotion in Airforce (Box 137)
      - Single woman denied abortion coverage (Box 137)
      - Student privacy rights (Box 137)
      - Wrongful imprisonment, Black Panther, 2 folders (Box 138)
      - Right to vote (Box 138)
      - School board elections, vote dilution, 2 folders (Box 138)
      - Dissemination of police records (Box 138)
      - Atomic energy and discharge of radioactive materials, 4 folders (Box 139)
      - Atomic energy and discharge of radioactive materials, 2 folders (Box 140)
      - Unresolved conflict of interest, 2 folders (Box 140)
      - Due process (Box 140)
      - Grades appeals (Box 140a)
      - Legality of missing school at parents' wishes (Box 140a)
      - Habeas corpus (Box 140a)
      - Unlawful stop, search, and seizure (Box 140a)
      - Prisoner treatment (Box 140a)
      - Habeas corpus (Box 140a)
      - Wrongful termination and subsequent denial of appeal (Box 140a)
      - Lease agreements (Box 140a)
      - Misc. correspondence (returned to sender) and prisoner correspondence (Box 140a)
      - Millbrook Underground Newspaper (Box 141)
      - Double jeopardy, habeas corpus (Box 141)
      - Compulsory sterilization of mentally ill, 4 folders (Box 141)
      - Wrongful imprisonment, murder (Box 141)
      - Wrongful expulsion, due process (Box 142)
      - Wrongful imprisonment (Box 142)
      - Stolen property (Box 142)
      - Wrongful termination of professor due to unclear contract (Box 142)
      - Sanctions against Rhodesia (Box 142)
      - NAACP (Box 142)
      - Prisoner treatment, assault (Box 142)
      - Employment discrimination, sex (Box 142)
      - Wrongful termination, due process (Box 142)
      - Rally ordinances (Box 142)
      - Deposit refund, client in jail (Box 142)
      - Prisoner treatment (Box 142)
      - City employee residency requirements (Box 142)
      - North Carolina Prisoners' Labor Union's affiliation with and invitations to prisoners (Box 142)
      - North Carolina Prisoners' Labor Union's affiliation with and invitations to prisoners, 2 folders (Box 143)
      - North Carolina Prisoners' Labor Union's affiliation with and invitations to prisoners: briefs and depositions, 2 folders (Box 143)
      - Denial of application due to citizenship (Box 143)
      - Involuntary sterilization (Box 143)
      - Prisoner's children put up for adoption (Box 144)
      - Habeas corpus, neglect of due process (Box 144)
      - Seventeen year old voting (Box 144)
      - Continuing education requirements for funeral directors and embalmers (Box 144)
      - Unlawful imprisonment, 2 folders (Box 144)
      - Discrimination against student even though previous charges were dropped (Box 144)
      - Firemen did not put out fire (Box 144)
      - Polk Youth Center (Box 144)
      - Discrimination, wrongful charges (Box 144)
      - Deprivation of medical care (Box 144)
      - Escaping prisoner shot (Box 144)
      - Voluntary waiver of rights (Box 145)
      - 1st amendment, "underground" newspaper (Box 145)
      - Elections to the State Board of Elections (Box 145)
      - Family harassed by sheriff (Box 145)
      - Due process (Box 145)
      - Habeas corpus (Box 145)
      - Prisoners and plea bargains, 2 folders (Box 145)
      - Illegal interrogation (Box 145)
      - Strip search of visitor to prison (Box 146)
      - Illegal search of boat by Customs officials (Box 146)
      - Due process for declaring a patient "mentally ill" (Box 146)
      - Alleged rape (Box 146)
      - Discrimination by beauty shop, racial discrimination (Box 146)
      - Prisoner treatment, 2 folders (Box 146)
      - Medicare claims (Box 146)
      - UNC-C, policy on legal name changes (Box 147)
      - Unlawful termination (Box 147)